this is the final version of our game gnome on a rope
the main mechanics is rope swinging the long can move left or right and adjust the rope's length there are
traps like spikes and blades touching them ends the game unless invincible mode dissolve where the gnome survives but the
steel shows blood the goal is to collect the treasure and reach the exit if I make it while holding
the treasure I win we also added a menu to resume or start the game that's the full side swing
avoid traps grab the treasure and escape now let's take a look at the game's architecture the main character is
the gnome built as a ragdoll it's made up of body parts like the head arms legs and torso
each part has a rigid body 2D connected with Unity joints so the gnome moves in a natural physics-based way
expand the gnome prefab in the Unity hierarchy point to head torso arms legs highlight rigid body 2D plus joint
2D components the gnome hangs from a rope which is created at runtime the rope is made of small physics
segments linked by joints giving it flexibility and swing players can extend or retract it with simple controls
now in play mode zoom in on rope segment clone objects in the hierarchy highlight rigid body 2D plus joint
2D press up or down to show extension and retraction controlling everything is the game manager this script handles the
main flow starting a new game resetting when the gnome dies checking if the treasure is collected and showing win
or game over screens
now let's open the game manager.cs in Visual Studio or Ryder
now briefly scroll through reset game check win and game over so the rugged doll gnome the rope system and
the game manager all work together to create the swinging mechanic and core game play zoom out in scene view
show gnome plus rope plus traps plus exit swing the gnome once the summarize visually
i'm going to walk you through the key code for this gnome game first the rope physics we will open
the rope script the rope is made of many small segments each segment has a rigid body 2D and the
spring joint we add and remove segment to lengthen or shorten the rope in create row segment function we instantiate
a segment and where it's joined to the chain in update function we change the top segments joint distance increasing
the distance makes the rope extend decreasing it shortens the rope a line renderer draws the rope visually by following
each segment position so physics comes from many rigid bodies linked by spring joints this makes swinging feels natural and
reactive to forces
next is collision and damage we will open the signal onouch script this script detects collision if the collider is
tag player it invokes a unity event that event is hoop to method in the scene for example traps traps
call game manager touch function or game manager.firetrop touch function and game manager then calls kill gnome function which plays
sounds and triggers the gnome death logic next is the gnome script destroy gnome function runs the death behavior it
can spawn prefabs like slices of things it also iterates every body part child
next is the body part script the detach function and parents apart and let it physic simulate independently later when
that part skips it removes it joints rigid bodies and colliders to clean up this decoupling keep physic cheap once
parts are out
next scoring here is simple the game main objective is the treasure when the gnome picks up the treasure we
call the game manager treasure collected function the set current gnome holding pressure is equal to true gnome updates the
arm is tried to show the pressure when player reaches the exit game manager that exit reach function checks holding
pressure if true the game plays the game over sound pauses time and shows the game over user interface so
this car is a boolean rule pressure collected equals win at exit
now the UI game manager holds references to three menus main menu gameplay menu and game over menu when the
game passes we set the time that time scale is equal to zero and toggle menu visibility resume sets time
that time scale is equal to one the invincible toggle reads the toggle state each frame in update function and
sets non invincible if invincible is true remove known function and destroy known function early out and the player won't
respond the main menu script starts background scene loading with load scene as it it shows a loading overlay and
then allow activation when the player presses new game
so a few small helpers make the game feel complete sprite swappers which is sprites for items spinner rotation animates
rotating traps remove after delay and resettable handle clean up and scene resets camera follow smoothly follows the gnome's position
within weeks next let's take a look at the asset and folder structure of the project inside the asset folder
I organize everything into subfolders we have here the script scenes and such in the script folder it contains all
the C# scripts like the rope scripts the manager scripts and such in the sprites folder here we have all
the 2D images and objects like traps no body parts treasure chest and such in the sound folder it stores
the background music and sound effects for traps death and pressure pickup for the scene folder we have the sample
scene that you repeat for the known folder we have the reusable objects like the rope segments the gnome rag
doll and more also we have the setting folder they stored the template the renderer 2D asset and such for
the text mesh text mesh pro folder it contains the font resources shaders and sprites for the project fonts for
the text and the other resources so outside the asset we also have the project setting folder which Unity uses
to store input physics and build settings and other required files like the readme file how to run the project
file the third party file for honesty and integrity and the release file for the project zip file also the
G ignore for the G to ignore the other files for submission I included a release zip file in the
repository inside it are assets project settings and the builds folder with a ready to run version to play just
extract the zip file and go to the builds folder on Windows run build.apk if you want to test it
in Unity open Unity Hub load the project open the main.csin and press play controls are simple arrow keys to
move left and right up and down arrows to change rope length and escape to pause there are few limitations
sometimes there basics can jitter when swinging very fast currently there's only one level adding more levels would improve replayability
we would also like to add more sounds effect particle effect and maybe high score system in the future version